James McNaughton Hester Papers MC.51
New York University Archives
James McNaughton Hester Papers
1960-1980
New York University Archives
Hester, James M., 1924-
MC.51
3.5 Linear Feet
James McNaughton Hester served at New York University as Dean of the Graduate School of Arts and Science and Executive Dean of Arts and Sciences from 1960-1961, and as University President from 1962-1975. He went on to serve as rector of the United Nations University from 1975-1980. The collection contains drafts and supporting materials from speeches, presentations and articles given and written by Hester between 1960-1980, as well as photographs, awards and clippings from his tenure at NYU.
Separated Materials
New York University 1832-1932, A Graphic Presentation Concerning New York University, and New York University Self-Study Report moved to stacks.
Biography of James McNaughton Hester
James M. Hester was born in Chester, Pennsylvania, on April 19, 1924, to James Montgomery and Margaret (McNaughton) Hester. Hester received his diploma from Woodrow Wilson High School in Long Beach, California, in 1942 and graduated with a Bachelor of Arts degree, summa cum laude in the humanities and magna cum laude in history, from Princeton University in 1945.
Hester served as a civil information and education officer with a military government team in the Fukuoka district of Japan following graduation and later obtained a Rhodes scholarship to attend Pembroke College of Oxford University, where he received a Bachelor of Arts in 1950. Hester also received his Master of Arts with second class honors in Philosophy, Politics and Economics in 1953 and Doctor of Philosophy in International Affairs in 1955 from Oxford University.
In 1957 Hester became Provost of Long Island University's Brooklyn Center and a member of the Board of Trustees of the Brooklyn Academy of Music. He was subsequently appointed Vice-President of Long Island University in 1958 and served as a member of the University's Board of Trustees from 1959-1960.
Hester was appointed Dean of the Graduate School of Arts and Science at New York University in 1960 and concurrently served as Executive Dean of Arts and Science and Professor of History. In 1962, Hester assumed the role of University President, which he occupied until his resignation in 1975 to become the first Rector of the United Nations University, where he remained until 1980.
He died in Princeton, New Jersey on December 31, 2014.
Scope and Content Note
The collection documents the activities of James Hester in his capacity as president of New York University and as rector of the United Nations University. A large part of the collection consists of speeches, remarks, interviews and articles given and written by Hester. The collection includes drafts, notes, research materials, correspondence regarding and reacting to his speeches and remarks. The collection also includes a large number of portrait photographs, honorary degrees awarded to Hester by other universities, and clippings about Hester's tenure at NYU.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series. The first series is arranged alphabetically. The second series is arranged chronologically according to when the speech, remark, presentation or article was made or published.
Missing Title
Personal
Speeches and Remarks
Related Materials at the New York University Archives
MC 149: James Hester Clippings Collection and RG 3.0.7: Records of the Office of the President (Dr. James McNaughton Hester).
Access Restrictions
Open to researchers.
Technical Requirement Note
Collection includes one 5'' reel to reel audio tape.
Speeches.; College Presidents -- New York (State) -- Biography; College Orations; Convocations; Commencement ceremonies; Clippings (information artifacts); New York University -- Presidents; New York University -- History -- Lectures
- Personal
  - Advocates, The, Channel 13, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alfred University Honorary Degree, 1965 June (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Allan Murray Cartter Memorial Book, 1976 October 21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Analysis of NYU for the Governor's and Regents' Select Committee on the Future of Private and Independent Higher Education, 1967 July 24 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Awards and Certificates, 1962-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1 of 2, 1946, 1960-1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 2 of 2, 1961-1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clippings ("The College Money Crunch" TV Broadcast, 1/3/74), 1973 December-1974 January (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence re. Appearance on "Today Show," Channel 4 (5/6/70), 1970 May (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hartwick College Honorary Degree, 1964 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Honorary Degree Awarded to J. P. Morgan, 1922 April-May (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Juan de Avalos Statue, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Lotos Club State Dinner, 1972 March-May (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Magazine Articles, 1962-1975 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Documents, 1970-1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous NYU Printed Materials, 1 of 2, 1968-1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous NYU Printed Materials, 2 of 2, 1962-1973 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Materials, 1966-1977 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - NYU Appointment as President, 1961 September-1963 January (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - NYU Farewell, 1975 April-July (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - NYU Student Publications, 1970 November-1975 April (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - NYU Torch Watercolor, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Pace College Honorary Degree, 1971 June (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Photograph (Unidentified Event), Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Photographs (College of Arts and Science Album), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Photographs (Portraits), 1 of 2, 1961-1971 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Photographs (Portraits), 2 of 2, 1961-1972 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Report to President Newsom by the Visiting Party from NYU to Ghana and Nigeria, 1961 May (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Transparencies (Possibly from a Presentation), Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Union Carbide and Ralph Nader, 1971 January (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Speeches and Remarks
  - Undated (The City and the University) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Undated Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Remarks Made During Executive Deanship, 1 of 2, [ca. 1960] - 1961 March 29 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Remarks Made During Executive Deanship, 2 of 2, 1961 January 29-1962 February 27 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Introduction to Higher Education in the United States (Convocation of the Inst. of Ed. of the University of London at NYU, 4/3/61), 1961 September-November (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Private Intellectual Life in a Free Society (Notes and Comments, Fall 61), 1961 September-November (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The Obligations of the Social Studies (Social Studies and Elementary School Teachers of the Garden City Public Schools, 9/5/61), 1961 September 5 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - This Week Magazine Article (1/62), 1961 December-1962 January (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Cultural Future of Brooklyn (Downtown Brooklyn Assoc., 1/22/62), 1962 January 18-February 2 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Communications in Education (Dateline, 2/16/62), 1962 January 12-April 26 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Westchester Science Fair Radio Show WFAS Awards Program (3/22/62), 1962 March-April (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Women of Tomorrow (Girls Clubs of America National Annual Conference, 3/26/62), 1961 December-1962 August (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Oxford-Cambridge (4/6/62), 1962 March-June (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Statement for NY World Telegram (4/18/62), 1962 April 18 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Education for the Exacting Demands of Our Times (NY State Association of School Superintendents, 9/25/62), 1962 September 25 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - The Private University in Our Tax Economy (Institute on Federal Taxation of NYU, 11/13/62), 1962 November 13 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - The Impact of Our Changing Values on Education (Council on Social Work Education, 1/23/63), 1963 January (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - The Generation of Hope (Commencement Address, 6/9/65), 1965 June 9 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Presidential Convocation for Students (9/66), 1966 September (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - NYU and NYU (Commerce and Industry Association of New York, 9/27/66), 1966 July-September (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - United Hospital Fund of NY (10/4/66), 1966 October-1968 January (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Inauguration of Provost Nelson (10/6/66), 1966 September-October (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Presidential Citation to Governor Paiwonsky (10/7/66), 1966 October (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Religion and Purposes of the University (Church of Ascension, 10/16/66), 1966 October 16 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Vision and Education (Society for the Prevention of Blindness, 11/17/66), 1966 November (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - The Land We Live In (St. Andrew's Society, 11/30/66), 1966 July-1967 January (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Testimony to the Subcommittee on Executive Reorganization (12/2/66), 1966 December (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Gallatin Dinner (12/8/66), 1966 July-December (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Greenwich Village Kiwanis Club (12/13/66), 1966 December (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - America's Radical Philosophy of Higher Education (Essay for Book "Something to Live For," 1/30/67), 1967 January 30 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Eckhouse Eulogy, Temple Emanu-El (2/1/67), 1967 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Morehouse College Centennial (2/18/67), 1967 February (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Jothan Johnson Service, Grace Church (3/4/67), 1967 March 4 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - D'Youville College, Buffalo (4/7/67), 1967 April-May (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Changing Role of Urban University (Univ. Club -4/8/67; Churchmen's Club - 4/11/67), 1967 April-May (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Our Public School Heritage (Long Beach Masonic Lodge, California - 4/28/67), 1967 April-May (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Commerce Alumni (5/3/67), 1967 May 3 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Hofstra Library Dedication (5/6/67), 1967 May 6 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Washington Square College Alumni Awards Dinner (5/10/67), 1967 February-May (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Graduate School of Social Work, Westinghouse University, Business City Conference (5/19/67), 1967 May (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Obligations of College Graduates (Commencement, Virginia State College, Norfolk, 5/30/67), 1966 September-1967 June (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Medical Leaders of the Future (Hahnemann Medical College, PA, Commencement, 6/1/67), 1967 May-June (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - The Demands of Being Human (Baccalaureate Address, 6/11/67), 1967 June-July (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - NYU Commencement (6/13/67), 1967 June 13 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Bronx Community College Commencement (6/15/67), 1967 June 15 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - WCBS Editorial, Blaine Amendment (7/11/67), 1967 July (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Management of a Large Private University (Haskins and Sells, 7/23/67), 1967 July 23 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Advice and Dissent Radio Program (7/30/67), 1967 July (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Personal Honor (Princeton University Freshmen, 9/12/67), 1965 February-1967 September (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Personal Honor (Presidential Convocation for Students, 9/16-9/18/67), 1967 September-1968 June (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Parents Convocation (9/16-9/20/67), 1967 September (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - New Constitution Education Aspect Vital to Private Universities (Alumni News 10/9/67), 1967 October 9 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - New York Times Interview (10/15/67), 1967 October 15 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Private Higher Education and the Future of NYC (Fifth Avenue Association, 10/19/67), 1967 June-October (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - The University and the Performing Arts (Fred Loewe Convocation, 10/24/67), 1967 October 24 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Constitution (Daily News Statement, 11/4/67), 1967 October-November (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - What Do We Ask of Religion (General Theological Seminary Anniversary, St. John the Divine, 11/8/67), 1967 November-1968 January (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Tensions Between Generations (Brotherhood Synagogue, 11/10/67), 1967 November-1968 May (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - SATO Convocation (11/17/67), 1965 December-1968 June (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - St. Nicholas Society (12/6/67), 1967 September-December (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Gallatin Dinner (12/7/67), 1967 June-December (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Ends and Means (Princeton University, 4/19/68), 1968 January-April (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - NYU and NYU (Bronx Rotary Club, 5/7/68), 1968 May-1969 October (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - NYU and NYU (NY Academy of Public Education, 5/7/68), 1967 November-1968 May (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Commencement Address Drafts (6/12/68), 1968 June 12 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Society's Best Instrument for Change (Commencement, 6/12/68), 1968 June-August (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Institute for Crippled and Disabled - Day Exercises (6/18/68), 1968 June (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - University and the City (Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, 8/28/68), 1968 August-December (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Meetings (Fall 68), 1968 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Tishman Dinner Lunch (Real Estate Industry, 9/9/68), 1968 September 9 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Education Faculty Meeting (9/11/68), 1968 September 11 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Presidential Convocation for Freshmen and Transfer Students (9/16/68), 1968 September 16 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Parents Convocation (9/18/68), 1968 September 18 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Pressures on the University Today (Investment Bankers Association, 10/3/68), 1968 October 3 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Salomon Lecture (11/14/68), 1968 November-1969 January (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Interaction Between University and Inner City (Regional Plan Association, 11/19/68), 1968 July-October (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Gallatin Dinner (12/4/68), 1968 December 4 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Martha Deane, WOR Interview (1/14/69), 1969 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Who Should Run the University?: Academia in Crisis (NYC Bar Association, 2/13/69), 1969 January-February (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Regarding the Future (Masonic Breakfast, 3/16/69), 1969 February-April (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Citation to Lord Balogh (3/19/69), 1969 March 19 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - New York Report (WOR-TV Interview, 3/23/69), 1969 March (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Martin Luther King Memorial Services (4/5/69), 1969 April 5 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Manhattan with Percy Sutton (4/21/69), 1969 April (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - The University and the Public: Crisis in Confidence (University Club, 4/22/69), 1969 April (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Newsmakers, WCBS Interviews (4/27/69), 1969 April (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Statement to New York Times (4/30/69), 1969 April 30 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Challenge to Higher Education Today (NY Chamber of Commerce, 5/1/69), 1969 May (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - The University and Community (Dorothy Gordon Youth Forum, WNBC, 5/4/69), 1969 April-May (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - University Undergoing Radical Changes (Guidance Counselors, Boston, 5/13/69), 1969 May 13 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - What Do We Ask of the Ministry (Crozer Theological Seminary Commencement, 6/3/69), 1969 May-July (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Student Activism (Trinity School Commencement 6/6/69), 1969 June 6 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Our National Morale (NYU Commencement, 6/11/69), 1969 June 11 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Neuman Award Remarks, Israel (7/22/69), 1969 July-November (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - GE College Bowl, One Minute Taped Spot (8/19/69), 1969 August (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Guidance Counselors (9/69), 1969 September (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Convocation for New Students (9/69), 1969 September (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Statement for Time Magazine (9/2/69), 1969 September 2 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - New York Tomorrow (American Jewish Committee, WNYC, 9/16/69), 1969 August 29 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Presidents to Presidents Conference Panel Participation (9/19/69), 1969 July-August (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Statement on Tax Reform Bill (9/25/69), 1969 September 25 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Washington Square College Faculty (10/7/69), 1969 October 7 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Dr. Wortis Memorial Service (10/8/69), 1969 October 8 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Institute of International Education, Annual Dinner (10/9/69), 1969 October (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - A Lesson from Israel (Hadassah, New Orleans, 10/14/69), 1969 August-November (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Martha Deane Radio Program Interview (10/15/69), 1969 October (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Arthritis Foundation (10/16/69), 1969 September-November (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Rye Country Day School Remarks (10/23/69), 1969 October (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Medical Faculty Remarks (10/28/69), 1969 October 28 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - ASPAU Conference (10/30/69), 1969 September-October (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Pressures on Urban University Today (YMCA, Princeton, 10/31/69), 1969 October-1971 August (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Corporation and the Campus (Council for Financial Aid and APS Symposium, 11/6/69), 1969 September-1970 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Los Angeles Alumni Remarks (11/14 and 12/16/69), 1969 November-December (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - One Approach to Higher Education (Campus in the City Conference, 12/2/69), 1969 October-December (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Gallatin Dinner (12/4/69), 1969 December (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Puerto Rico Commencement (12/6/69), 1969 December (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Federal Business Association Lunch (12/9/69), 1969 December (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - The New Concept of "Community" (The Corporation and the Campus, 70), 1970 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - NYU Education Quarterly, Taped Interview (1/70), 1969 June-1970 January (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - The Condition of the Christian Layman (Council of Churches, 1/22/70), 1969 November-1970 May (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - The Competing Claims of Liberal and Professional Education in the Modern University (University of Lagos, Nigeria Lecture, 2/20/70), 1970 February 20 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - The Presidents Association, Inc. Interview (3/70), 1970 February (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Kenan Inaugural Lecture (3/12/70), 1970 March 12 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - University Christian Foundation (3/18/70), 1970 February-May (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - National Institute on Sex Education (3/18/70), 1969 December-1970 April (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - The Student Role in the University (Institute of International Education, 3/19/70), 1969 December-1970 March (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Redefining the Educated Man (Syracuse University, 3/19/70), 1970 March-July (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - GBA Alumni Business Conference - Taggart Remarks (3/21/70), 1970 March (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Student Participation in Academic Governance (American Association of Dental Schools, 3/22/70), 1969 November-1970 April (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - New York Times Interview (4/9/70), 1970 April (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Martha Deane Radio Show (4/14/70), 1970 April (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Irving Kristol Lecture (4/15/70), 1970 April 15 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Statement to the Select Sub-Committee on Education of the Education and Labor Committee (4/24/70), 1970 April-May (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Problems of the Urban University (Texaco Round Table, 4/30/70), 1970 March-May (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Issues in Higher Education (University Heights, Philosophy on Education, 4/30/70), 1970 March-April (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - "Role of Police in Urban Society" A Preceptorship (4/30/70), 1970 February (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - The Academic Revolution (Magazine Publishers Association, 5/19/70), 1970 March-May (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Newsweek Interview (5/20/70), 1970 May (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Issues and Answers, Channel 7 (5/31/70), 1970 May-June (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Spence School Commencement Address (6/4/70), 1970 June (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - International Association of Universities, Montreal (8/31/70), 1970 August (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Ladies' Home Journal Article (9/70), 1970 May-September (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Some Observations on the Urban Involvement of Universities (Urban Affairs Quarterly, 9/70), 1970 February-September (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - The University President and Student Unrest (National Association of College Admissions Counselors, 10/1/70), 1970 October (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Matha Deane Show (10/1/70), 1970 October-1971 February (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - E. Harris Harbison and Good Teaching (Haribson Award Ceremony, 10/18/70), 1970 October (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - U.S. News and World Report Quote (10/19/70), 1970 October 19 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Campaign Plus 1 Presidential Message (10/22/70), 1970 October 22 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Heights Alumni (10/29/70), 1970 October 29 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Problems of Student Unrest at NYU (Men in Finance Club, 10/30/70), 1970 September-October (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - College Students and Foreign Policy (Foreign Policy Association, 11/4/70), 1970 July-November (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Youth, the City and Education (Packer Collegiate Institute, 11/7/70), 1970 November-1971 March (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - History of NYU (Newcomen Society, 11/12/70), 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - The University President and Student Unrest (American Petroleum Institute, 11/18/70), 1970 October-November (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - G. Knoop Sculpture Dedication (11/20/70), 1970 November 20 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - NYU Law School - Dean's Day (11/21/70), 1970 January-1971 January (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Southern California Alumni Dinner Dance (11/28/70), 1970 November (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Gallatin Dinner (12/3/70), 1970 November-December (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Freshmen (71), 1971 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - The American Oxonian Interview (1/71), 1971 January (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Presbyterian Life Interview (1/15/71), 1970 December-1971 February (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - The Campus Now (Real Estate Institute, 1/19/71), 1971 January 19 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - The Campus Now (Soap and Detergent Association, 1/27/71), 1970 December-1971 February (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - NYU Medical School - Dean's Day (2/15/71), 1970 December-1971 February (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Higher Education: The Critical Issues (Regents Annual Conference, 2/18/71), 1970 July-1971 February (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Testimony Before the Subcommittee on Appropriations for Labor, Health, Education and Welfare (3/10/71), 1971 February-April (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - University Heights Presbyterian Church Sermon (3/14/71), 1970 November-1971 April (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - George Washington University American Studies Program (3/17/71), 1971 March (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Statements of Higher Education Association - House of Representatives (3/30/71), 1971 March (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - American Oxonian Interview (4/71), 1971 January-April (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - National Council on Philanthropy (4/13/71), 1971 February-April (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Opinion Editorial Draft (Not Submitted, 4/16/71), 1971 April (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Commerce Alumni (5/13/71), 1971 May 13 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Fordham Commencement (6/5/71), 1971 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - NYU Commencement (6/7/71), 1971 May-June (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Durable Need and Perpetual Challenge for Academic Libraries (Dedication of Univ. of Pittsburgh Library (6/13/71), 1971 June (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Crisis in Higher Education in NYC (Rotary Club of NY, 6/17/71), 1971 June (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Educators Conference in Nara, Japan (6/27/71-7/3/71), 1971 June-July (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Parents Convocation (9/71), 1971 September (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Testimony for ACUNY Beofre the Board of Regents Legislative Conference (9/9/71), 1971 June-September (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Testimony Before the Joint Legislative Committee on Higher Education (9/23/71), 1971 September (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Preface Written for the Iran Volume (9/24/71), 1971 September (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - ORT 21st Biennial Convention (10/71), 1970 March-1971 July (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Inauguration of H. B. Whiteman Jr. (Sweet Briar College, 10/13/71), 1971 October-1972 March (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - The Church, the University and the City (Central Presbyterian Church, 10/17/71), 1971 May-October (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Mandate 81 Convocation, Georgetown University (10/23/71), 1971 October-November (Box 4, Folder 36)